Guide to the Charles Robert Leslie Collection
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
Charles Robert Leslie Collection
1812-1900
MSS 15
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
2
1 box + 5 volumes
The collection comprises sketchbooks, writings, and correspondence by Charles Robert Leslie (1794-1859) and his family.
Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859
Leslie, Bradford, 1831-1926
Leslie, George Dunlop, 1835-1921
Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879
Leslie, Harriet Jane, 1828-1864
Leslie, Mary, 1833-1907
Maclise, Daniel, 1806-1870
Powell, Peter, ca. 1775-1855
Biographical / Historical
Charles Robert Leslie (19 October 1794- 5 May 1859) was born in London to American parents, Robert Charles (d. 1804) and Lydia Leslie (ca. 1766-1824). His father was a prosperous Philadelphia clockmaker who moved his family to England in 1793 to expand his business. The Leslies' time in America was short-lived, however, and they returned to Philadelphia in 1799. Charles showed an early talent for drawing, which was fostered through classes taken at the University of Pennsylvania at the young age of ten. Upon his father's death in 1804, however, the family encountered financial hardships and there were no funds with which to further Charles's artistic education.
In 1808, he became a publisher's apprentice at the press of Bradford and Inskeep in Philadelphia. A senior partner of the firm, after seeing a promising watercolor that Leslie had made of actor Frederick Cooke, helped him to enroll at the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts. The senior partner, Samuel Bradford, also raised money to help send Charles to London for artistic training. The Academy was impressed with Charles's work and, in addition to accepting him as a student, helped to support his study abroad. Those in America who saw Charles's paintings were struck with their potential and fervently supported his pursuit of a career in painting.
Once he arrived in London in 1811, Charles Robert Leslie was instructed and strongly influenced by Benjamin West, the president of the Royal Academy, as well as Washington Allston and Samuel F.B. Morse (who, although then studying painting, would go on to fame as the inventor of Morse code). Morse and Leslie were students together at the Royal Academy, where Leslie had enrolled in 1813. Although his American-born mentors were history painters, Leslie's longstanding interest in the stage remained a prevalent feature of his work.
Leslie traveled to France in 1817, accompanied by his friend, William Collins (who would become the father of writer Wilkie Collins), and his mentor, Washington Allston. Collins was a close associate of the successful painter, David Wilkie, whose genre paintings were garnering considerable attention and praise. While painting portraits to support himself and to keep his work in public view, Leslie took note of genre painting and began to move into this field. Allston helped to secure work for Leslie as an illustrator of Washington Irving's works, Knickerbocker's History of New York and The Sketch Book. Leslie would carry on his friendship with Washington Irving for the rest of his life.
In 1819, Leslie exhibited his painting, Sir Roger de Coverley Going to Church, a genre piece that received a favorable response. Leslie continued creating literary genre paintings throughout the next several years, becoming a member of the Royal Academy in 1826. By 1820, Leslie, who had been supported by the Pennsylvania Academy of the Arts throughout his tenure in England, decided to stay in London. He married Harriet Honor Stone (1799-1879) in 1825. Together, they would have six children, including George Dunlop Leslie, who became a celebrated genre painter like his father. Among Leslie's other children, his son Robert Charles and daughter Mary would also follow his footsteps into painting and book illustration.
Leslie's trajectory of success was stymied, to some extent, in 1833, when his brother Tom, who had made a career in the U.S. Army, obtained a position for Leslie at West Point Academy in New York. Leslie was eventually persuaded to travel to the United States to take the post as a drawing teacher, but he and his family remained there only five months, suffering through a bitter winter and various disappointments. They returned to London in 1834.
Despite the hardships of the brief stint at West Point, Leslie would receive his most important commission just a few years later, in 1838. Patrons Baron and Lady Holland arranged for him to attend the coronation of Queen Victoria. The Queen ultimately commissioned Leslie's picture of the event, entitled Queen Victoria Receiving the Sacrament After the Coronation. She would also commission a second piece in 1841, this time depicting the christening of the Princess Royal. The royal commissions were career-making events for Leslie, who went on to paint further genre and literary works on commission for the rest of his life and to become a professor of painting at the Royal Academy in 1847. He moved in influential creative circles, both artistic and literary. Before his death in 1859, Leslie published a biography of Sir John Constable, a Handbook for Young Painters, and began work on his autobiography as well as on a work about Sir Joshua Reynolds. The latter two books were published posthumously. C.R. Leslie was buried in Kensal Green Cemetery in London. His art hangs in museum and private collections on both sides of the Atlantic, testifying to his successful negotiation of the American and British worlds of early nineteenth century painting.
Mary Leslie (1833-1907) was the fifth child of Charles Robert and Harriet Honor Leslie. She showed a keen artistic talent, and became a book illustrator. She remained unmarried throughout her life, living with her mother and sister Harriet after her father's death. Her sister died in 1864, and her mother in 1884. Mary appears to have had some kind of mental or neurological health crisis around this time. In 1891, she is listed as a boarder at a home in Berkshire, near the residence of her brother George. Strikingly, she is recorded as an "imbecile" in this census, and a nurse, Bessie Robertson, is shown in the same household. By 1901, Mary had moved into George's home, Riverside, in Berkshire, and is again listed as an "imbecile" in that year's census. A slightly cryptic note in one of Mary's sketchbooks, penned by her brother George, says that in later life Mary's "balance had gone" and that she only had one eye. Mary Leslie died in 1907, in Lindfield, Sussex, England.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Yale Center for British Art, Paul Mellon Collection
Arrangement
The collection is divided into three series: I. Albums and sketchbooks; II. Writings; III. Correspondence.
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises sketchbooks, writings, and correspondence by Charles Robert Leslie (1794-1859) and his family. Leslie was known best for his paintings of literary subjects, although his oeuvre included portraiture, history paintings, and selected literary works. The collection was compiled by Leslie's son, George Dunlop Leslie, also a celebrated genre painter, and represents the years, 1812 to 1900. The collection includes documents related to Leslie's wife, Harriet, as well as some of his children, Mary, Harriet, George, and Robert Charles. Additional materials include correspondence from Tom Taylor and Peter Powell, representing some of Leslie's most important professional and personal relationships.
The largest portion of correspondence comprises letters from Leslie's wife, Harriet. The letters were originally placed in a paper folder (appearing to date from the time of George Dunlop's selection of these items) with a note reading, "Letters cheifly [sic] from Mrs Leslie to C.R. Leslie RA mostly from different sea-side places. Broadstairs, Benbridge, Brighton, etc. dates between 1836 1850. also some from the children at the same time to their father C.R. Leslie./ also a few answers from CRL/ very amusing & characteristic examined & selected by G.D. Leslie 1898."
Bibliography
Evans, Dorinda. "Charles Robert Leslie." Oxford Dictionary of National Biography, online. http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/16485
Leslie, R.C. (Robert Charles). A Waterbiography. London: Chapman and Hall, Ltd., 1894.
Dance -- Pictorial works; Military uniforms -- Great Britain; Painters -- Great Britain; Painting -- Great Britain; Painting, British -- 19th century; Panoramas; Albums (Books); Autobiographies; Cut-paper works; Graphite drawings; Pen and ink drawings; Letters; Sketchbooks; Watercolors; Brand, John, 1744-1806; Browne, William, 1590-approximately 1645; Chaucer, Geoffrey, -1400; Grose, Francis, 1731?-1791; Hogarth, William, 1697-1764; Hollar, Wenceslaus, 1607-1677; Leslie, Bradford, 1831-1926; Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859 -- Correspondence; Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859; Leslie, George Dunlop, 1835-1921; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; Leslie, Harriet Jane, 1828-1864; Leslie, Mary, 1833-1907; Leslie, Robert C. (Robert Charles), 1826-1901; Leslie, Robert, -1804; Leslie, Thomas Jefferson, 1796 or 1797-1874; Maclise, Daniel, 1806-1870; Morse, Samuel Finley Breese, 1791-1872; Powell, Peter, ca. 1775-1855; Taylor, Tom, 1817-1880; West, Benjamin, 1738-1820; Royal Academy of Arts (Great Britain)
- Albums and Sketchbooks, Series I
  - Charles Robert Leslie sketchbook, circa 1820-1859; Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859; 1 album (110 pages); 21 cm. Bound in contemporary vellum. (Box Vol. 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Inscribed at front: "C.R. Leslie. No. 8 Buckingham Place, Fitzroy Sq., London, Jany. 1815." The album includes a mixture of texts and drawings.
    Texts include: "Extracts from Grose's Antiquities, continued from my sketch book dated July 9th, 1813"; "Extracts descriptive of the festivities of May Day"; and various notes on Hall, Browne (his Britannius pastorals ), Borlose, Brand (his Observations on popular antiquities ), Hollar, and Hogarth.
    The volume include 15 drawings in graphite and 39 drawings in pen and black ink. Accompanying the extracts from Grose's Antiquities are a number of full-page drawings, in graphite, of men in military costume, along with depictions of various weaponry and armor. The ink drawings primarily depict figures in historical dress. It's possible that some of these are depictions of characters from the stage.
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Yale Center for British Art, Paul Mellon Collection
    Pen and ink drawings; Graphite drawings; Military uniforms -- Great Britain; Sketchbooks; Hogarth, William, 1697-1764; Hollar, Wenceslaus, 1607-1677; Browne, William, 1590-circa 1645; Brand, John, 1744-1806; Grose, Francis, 1731?-1791
  - Charles Robert Leslie album, 1850; Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859; 1 album (128 pages); 32 cm. Bound in black half morocco and blue cloth. (Box Vol. 2)
    The spine of the volume bears a paper label inscribed: "Sketches by C.R. Leslie, R.A., selected by G.D.L. [i.e. George Dunlop Leslie] '06."
    The album comprises 103 drawings or groups of drawings by Leslie, all on small sheets affixed to blank leaves in the album. These includes 66 drawings in pen and ink (frequently over graphite) and 37 drawings in graphite; 8 of the drawings include some addition of watercolor.
    Most drawings are unsigned and without labels. There are a number of quickly drawn studies of men and women in common dress. A series of drawings near the front depict various ensembles of figures dancing; one of these is labeled "Espaja [?] Spy glass." As in the preceding C.R. Leslie sketchbook in this collection, a number of the drawings depict figures in historical costume, especially of the 17th century. Some of these may be depictions of characters from the stage. Titled portraits depict the likes of John Constable, Richard Fanshawe, William Duke of Hamilton, David Leslie, and Catherine of Aragon; most (if not all) of these are copies.
    Watercolors; Military uniforms -- Great Britain; Dance -- Pictorial works; Sketchbooks; Graphite drawings; Pen and ink drawings; Leslie, George Dunlop, 1835-1921
  - Mary Leslie sketchbook (1), 1865; Leslie, Mary, 1833-1907; 1 album (26 pages); 16 cm. Bound in blind-stamped red calf, with copper clasps (intact); all edges gilt. (Box Vol. 3)
    The album is inscribed at front: "Eleven drawings & two cuttings, 1865." In fact, the album comprises 16 drawings and two cut-paper works, to which have been inserted three additional sheets containing five more drawings. About half of the drawings are finished in watercolor. Most of the drawings depict young ladies in various fashions; some depict children. The two cut-paper works depict a wading bird and a semi-abstract collection of flowers. At the end is tipped in a printed page of "Isabella, or The pot of basil, a story from Bocaccio."
    Graphite drawings; Botanical illustrations; Cut-paper works; Sketchbooks; Clothing and dress -- Great Britain; Watercolors; Fashion -- Great Britain
  - Mary Leslie sketchbook (2), circa 1860-1900; Leslie, Mary, 1833-1907; 1 album (56 pages); 18 x 11 cm. Bound in blind-stamped green cloth. (Box Vol. 4)
    This small sketchbook contains 72 mounted illustrations, which include pen and ink drawings, graphite sketches, watercolors, and cut-paper works.
    The cut-paper works include finely detailed textual and graphic pieces, such as a small mounted image of flowers and thistles which bears the legend, "Dieu et mon Droit." Another cut out piece depicts the scene of a hunt (perhaps inspired by the paintings of Stubbs), with a ferocious lion leaping to sink his teeth into a racing antelope.
    Mary Leslie's watercolor illustrations include a charming depiction of a small grey and black striped cat sitting by beehives in a colorful stylized garden. Attention to composition, color, and detail are clear in this small image, created as though in the form of a panel illustration.
    Tiny graphite and pen and ink panel-style drawings, some of which were eventually published, show animals and pastoral scenes. A quartet of tiny mounted panels shows antelope or deer fleeing a hunter's arrow, sheep grazing peacefully by night, a squirrel holding an acorn, and a shepherd with his flock. All of the images are composed with a view to their decorative effect, tightly structured and arranged within miniscule rectangular spaces.
    Mary's marine landscapes and studies of shells in graphite and watercolor show a sophisticated grasp of natural subjects.
    The album also includes graphite illustrations of biblical scenes, such as Noah releasing the dove from the ark and the infant Moses discovered in a basket. Composition and technique--tight structure, emphasis on surfaces and draped human figures, for example--may evidence some influence from contemporary Victorian art, such as that of the pre-Raphaelites or the St. John's Wood Clique, of which her brother George was a member.
    George Dunlop Leslie included a couple of notes in ink, written on pages of the album, to indicate further information about his sister's work. On a page of mounted miniature panels and motifs, he writes, "These and those on the following Pages are designs for 'Breaks' for a work on the 'Song of the three children' published by J. Murray (in wood cut)."
    There are a few charming graphite images of women and children. One image shows a mother feeding her child at a table. A small sketch mounted just below shows a toddler grasping a kitten around the neck. A later image shows a young woman holding a book. She wears an elaborate dotted dress, with frilled cuffs. The clothing depicted in these scenes suggests that they date from the 1860s.
    A series of intricate paper cut outs is labeled, by George, as follows: "These cut paper designs were done quite late in her life when her balance was gone, they show however how true her artistic power remained. They were cut out without any preliminary drawing. She had but one eye but her eyesight must have been marvelous/ GDL."
    Sketchbooks; Botanical illustrations; Watercolors; Graphite drawings; Pen and ink drawings; Cut-paper works
- Writings and Manuscripts, Series II
  - Autobiography, circa 1836-1857; Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859; 431 pages; 33 cm. Bound in contemporary sheep. (Box Vol. 5)
    Original autograph manuscript of C.R. Leslie's autobiography (published as: Autobiographical recollections by the late Charles Robert Leslie, R.A. London: John Murray, 1860).
    The manuscript is written in pen and ink, in Leslie's hand throughout. It is heavily revised and edited. A significant number of passages here were omitted in the published version, edited by Tom Taylor.
    Mounted at front is the engraved trade card of Leslie's father: "Leslie & Price, Clock & Watch Makers, no. 79 Market Street, Philadelphia."
    Trade cards (advertising); Painting, British -- 19th century; Painters -- Great Britain; Autobiographies; Taylor, Tom, 1817-1880; Leslie, Robert, -1804; Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859
  - Thoughts on Painting, circa 1845; Leslie, Mary, 1833-1907; 8 leaves; 18 x 22 cm. Sewn. Written in pen and brown/black ink with watercolor illustration. (Box 1, Folder A)
    Manuscript treatise, bound by hand. Mary Leslie declares, "I am going to lay before you...my inexpeareanced [sic] thoughts on the subject of painting." It is likely that Mary created this piece while still a young child. She writes of her previous ignorance, looking at "those unatureal [sic] painters, Landsear [sic], Redgrave, Danby, and many others..." Mary goes on to praise Raphael for his lack of affectation, and then speaks warmly of Turner and Constable, writing that she has heard people say that "Constable painted, silver. Turner painted, Gold" [sic] as a way of comparing the two. She concludes by saying that she has other thoughts on the subject of painting, but they are difficult to write down.
    Painting, British -- 19th century; Painters -- Great Britain
  - The Flower and the Leaf of Chaucer, illustrated, circa 1885; Leslie, Mary, 1833-1907; Leslie, George Dunlop, 1835-1921; 18 pages; 23 x 15 cm. Edged/partially bound with tape on one side, with an additional page mounted on a cardboard sheet. (Box 1, Folder B)
    Attributed to George Leslie but bearing strong resemblances to the work of Mary Leslie, this manuscript appears to be a mockup for an unpublished edition of Chaucer's poem, "The Flower and the Leaf." The poem is copied out by hand in a small, cursive hand, and each page has illustrated panels depicting scenes from the poem, with decorative borders. The intricate details and carefully drawn figures in medieval costume evoke the Victorian fascination and interpretation of medieval aesthetics. Naturalistic embellishments in the page borders, including drawings of flowers, birds, insects, and reeds at water's edge, are done in a careful and moderately skillful hand.
    Pen and ink drawings; Poems; Watercolors; Chaucer, Geoffrey, -1400
- Correspondence, Series III
  - Bradford Leslie
    - Letter to George Dunlop Leslie, circa 1845-1852; Leslie, Bradford, 1831-1926; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 18 x 22 cm. Autograph letter, signed, written in pen and brown/black ink, with pen and ink illustration. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Bradford Leslie writes to his brother George, including a comical sketch of pigs lolling in the grass. He comments on the "porkers," saying that they "will explain to you how hot it is here." It is likely that this letter was written while Bradford was completing his engineering apprenticeship; he mentions the town of St. Briavels, which is in Gloucestershire, not far from Chepstow, where Bradford would go in 1851-2 as part of his apprenticeship. Bradford comments on the animals he sees in the area, as well as on the rock in the region, which he says is called "pudding stone." He notes the cheapness of the home prices in the town and remarks that he wants to make a "rod" out of sticks he has found.
      Correspondence; Leslie, Bradford, 1831-1926 -- Correspondence; Leslie, George Dunlop, 1835-1921 -- Correspondence
  - Charles Robert Leslie
    - Letter to Thomas Leslie, 1812 February 2; Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859; 6 pages (2 folded leaves); 32 x 40 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      The letter is sent from No. 82, Great Titchfield Street, Fitzroy Square, addressed to Thomas Leslie at Number 48 South Sixth Street, Philadelphia. Charles writes a lengthy letter to his brother, telling him of his experiences in London during his artistic training. He acknowledges a recent letter from Thomas that arrived on the Anna Maria and makes some remarks and inquiries about mutual acquaintances, mentioning a captain who is sailing to America and a picture that Thomas is obtaining from Sully (i.e. Thomas Sully?), as well as a picture offered by Carpenter. He jokingly sends his love to a woman described as his "destined bride," suggesting that a woman in Philadelphia believes that they have formed an attachment that does not exist. Leslie writes of taking lodgings with "Mr [Samuel F.B.] Morse a son of the celebrated geographer." He writes of his deep friendship with Morse, with whom he lives "like brothers." Leslie goes on to describe his living arrangement and routine dining. He mentions dining "a few days ago with Mr [Benjamin] West" and a few other people; their party "consisted [mostly] of Americans." Leslie comments that West mentions a "tavern in Strawberry Alley" where "two of his early pictures" are and where he first "discovered a taste for painting." Leslie describes West's upcoming project of a "picture of Christ before Pilate," anticipating it to be "equal to any thing of Raphael's or Michael Angelo's." Leslie plans to draw a bust of West, which Morse has recently bought, and send it to Thomas.
      Leslie goes on to mention that West has given him "a note of introduction to Fuseli at the Royal Academy." He notes, however, that he does not go often to the academy because, "the accommodations for students are so very bad...the figures [for drawing] are discoloured, the room so badly lighted that you can't see the outline distinctly, and generally very crowded with students..." He says that he and Morse often draw from casts at home, returning them for half price when they are through with them. Leslie writes of trying to visit the Horse Armoury (at the Tower of London), but being charged full price and then being denied permission to make sketches.
      Leslie reports having gone to see "Mr Barker's panoramas, the seige [sic] of Flushing, and Bay of Messina they are so well painted as to be quite deception [sic], particularly the latter one, as they extend in a circular form all round the rooms and the spectators are placed in the center the effect is very astonishing, I actually put on my hat imagining myself to be in the open air." He comments that the painting is so effective that it was impossible to tell how far the canvas was from him, seeming even "thirty miles off" at one point.
      Charles writes that he has not been much to the theater, as it is repetitive and he is tired of pantomimes. He writes that "Mrs Siddons is to quit the stage after this season," and is currently performing in Edinburgh. "When she returns," he vows, "I shall go almost every night, as I never expect to see such another woman."